{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Charles E. Mitchell briefly halted this event, which was predicted by Roger Babson’s namesake “break.” Richard Whitney attempted to curtail the damage caused by this event, which was studied by the Pecora Commission. The Glass-Steagall Act was passed in the wake of this event and required commercial and investment banking operations to be separated. Margin calls fueled panic on “Black Monday” and “Black Tuesday” during, for ten points, what inciting incident of the Great Depression?",
      "answer": "Wall Street crash of 1929 or stock market crash of 1929"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the leadup to this war, Ansar al-Islam was defeated in the north by a CIA-supported force from the Peshmerga. Lynndie England was imprisoned for dereliction of duty during this war for mistreating POWs. Four years after his war began, a “surge” strategy was employed by the commander of the Multi National Force, David Petraeus. Colin Powell argued at the UN that the presence of weapons of mass destruction was enough pretext to launch, for ten points, what war that toppled Saddam Hussein?",
      "answer": [
        "Iraq War",
        "Operation Iraqi Freedom",
        "Second Persian Gulf War, but do not"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Note: two answers required. The Seven Missions territory changed hands in a 1750 treaty between these two countries. The bull Aeterni Regis signified papal approval of a treaty signed between these two countries. Both of these countries’ claims to the Moluccas Islands led to the 1529 Treaty of Zaragoza, a follow-up to an earlier agreement that a line 370 leagues west of the Cape Verde Islands would be used to separate New World claims. The Treaty of Tordesillas was signed by, for ten points, what two Iberian countries?",
      "answer": "Spain and Portugal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man and John Stott co-founded the Lausanne Movement. This deliverer of the “My Hope America” speech said “We have to stand in the middle in order to preach to all people” as a reason why he refused to join Jerry Falwell’s Moral Majority. Hour of Decision was broadcast in the early 1950s by this man, who went on hundreds of namesake Christianizing crusades. For ten points, name this celebrity Southern Baptist evangelist who advised twelve US Presidents.",
      "answer": "William Franklin “Billy” Graham Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "This character uses the informal insult “Casse toi” [cah-say TWAH] in his opening appearance before declaring himself “the best.” This figure, who announces “I’m takin’ this horse by the reins, makin’ Redcoats redder with bloodstains,” tries to rhyme “anarchy” with “monarchy” shortly before Hercules Mulligan and John Laurens give their verses in the song “My Shot.” Daveed Diggs portrayed Thomas Jefferson and this man in the original Broadway cast of Hamilton. For ten points, name this marquis who aided the colonies during the American Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette",
        "either",
        "both underlined names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was the site of a 1911 uprising remembered by the Yellow Flower Mound. The Whampoa Military Academy was founded in this city, which was made a treaty port under the Nanking Treaty. The Thirteen Factories were located in this city, where Hongs managed trade with Europeans. This port city on the Pearl River was connected to Hong Kong via the Kowloon-Canton Railway in 1910. For ten points, name this southern Chinese city in Guangdong.",
      "answer": "Guangzhou or Canton before mentioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "A composer from this country who wrote a series of Chˆoros [SHO-roos] and took inspiration from Bach for his Bachianas was commissioned to write his Third Symphony, subtitled “War,” as a celebration of the Treaty of Versailles. A major event in this country calls for afoxˆe music and involves a music competition that takes place at the Sambadrome. Heitor Villa-Lobos is from this country, where Antonio Carlos Jobim and Jo˜ao Gilberto popularized bossa nova. For ten points, name this South American country where samba music is played in the Carnival parades in Rio de Janeiro.",
      "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil"
    },
    {
      "question": "Karl Radek argued against signing this treaty, arguing that revolutions would soon occur that would render it unnecessary. This treaty, whose terms were annulled in the Treaty of Rapallo, made the Kars Oblast an Ottoman territory. Demands for “peace, land, and bread” fueled one side to accept the harsh terms of this treaty, which included giving control of the Baltic States to Germany. For ten points, name this 1918 treaty that took Russia out of World War I.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Brest-Litovsk"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s reputation was hurt when his aide John Armstrong attempted to launch a coup in the Newburgh Conspiracy. The Conway Cabal aimed to place this man in full command of the army. Cornwallis routed this man’s forces at the Battle of Camden in 1780, three years after this man was more successful in forcing the surrender of John Burgoyne in New York. For ten points, name this colonial commander who won the Battle of Saratoga.",
      "answer": "Horatio Gates"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader oversaw the abolition of privy purses by passing the 26th constitutional amendment in 1971. This leader’s son Sanjay advocated for a mass sterilization program that this leader implemented during a period known as the Emergency. This leader was assassinated in retaliation for launching a military assault on Amritsar’s Golden Temple as part of Operation Blue Star. For ten points, name this daughter of Jawarhalal Nehru, the first female Prime Minister of India.",
      "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A politician from this country reportedly held up a copy of The Constitution of Liberty by Austrian thinker Friedrich von Hayek and stated “This is what we believe.” Another economist from this country used wine from Portugal and cloth from this country to define comparative advantage in trade. A political economist from this country wrote On Liberty and Utilitarianism. For ten points, name this home country of David Ricardo and John Stuart Mill.",
        "answer": [
          "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland or U.K.",
          "Great Britain",
          "England"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to the legend, this Conservative politician wielded Hayek’s The Constitution of Liberty in 1975, while she served as Leader of the Opposition during Harold Wilson’s government.",
        "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a work partially named for this figure, Minerva points to a printing press near famed inventors and Liberty holds a fasces and wears a Phrygian cap. This figure leans on his horse at Verplanck’s Point in New York in a John Trumbull work that was followed by a similar pose of this man in front of Evacuation Day proceedings. The government commissioned Constantino Brumidi to paint the Apotheosis of this leader for the US Capitol rotunda. For ten points, name this man whose portrait was saved by Dolley Madison during the burning of D.C. in 1814.",
        "answer": "George Washington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the inventors near Minerva in The Apotheosis of Washington was this man, who built the first practical submarine for Napoleon and the Clermont, the first commercially successful steamboat.",
        "answer": "Robert Fulton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was aided by the militaristic Blue Shirts Society in enforcing traditional values during the New Life Movement. After this leader was kidnapped in the Xi’an [shee-ahn] incident, he was strong-armed into forming a “Second United Front” to fight Japan. This successor of Sun Yat-sen established a government in Taiwan after losing a civil war to the Communists. For ten points, name this Nationalist leader who was defeated by Mao Zedong.",
        "answer": "Chiang Kai-shek"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Xi’an Incident took place as Japan’s Kwantung Army, whose leader included this man, occupied Manchuria and threatened war with China. This man later served as Japan’s Minister of War and Prime Minister during most of World War II.",
        "answer": "Hideki Tojo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hot deck imputation used by this agency was ruled constitutional in the case Utah v. Evans. Robert W. Marx helped create the TIGER system for this agency, and it also used the UNIVAC I computer. Frederick Jackson Turner developed the Frontier Thesis after this agency stopped tracking the frontier in 1890. Federal courts have blocked this agency from including a citizenship question in its upcoming forms. The U.S. Federal Statistical System includes, for ten points, what agency that, since 1790, has tabulated data about the American people every 10 years?",
        "answer": "U.S. Census Bureau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 19th century, a US Census statistician discovered the Alabama paradox when trying to carry out this process, the constitutionally mandated purpose of the census.",
        "answer": [
          "apportionment of the House of Representatives",
          "descriptive answers regarding “calculating how many representatives in Congress each state will have”"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An Adele Berlin article about “[this book] and Ancient Storytelling” argues that it was meant to be a historical novella. Herodotus’ description of the domineering Amestris is associated by some scholars with this book’s character of Vashti, who is ousted as queen for refusing to appear at a banquet. King Ahasuerus is saved by Mordecai and the plot of Haman is thwarted in, for ten points, what book of the Old Testament, named for a queen of Persia, that depicts the origins of Purim?",
        "answer": "Book of Esther"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Ahasuerus is most frequently identified with this Persian ruler, who ruled from 486 to 465 BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Xerxes the Great",
          "Xerxes I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler deposed his client king, Cotys I of the Bosporan kingdom, in favor of annexing the Crimean Peninsula. This emperor used a collapsible boat in an attempt to kill his mother; when that failed, he killed her with an assassin. This ruler committed suicide in 68 AD after it was clear Galba would take over. For ten points, name this adopted son of Claudius, a Roman emperor who legendarily fiddled while Rome burned.",
        "answer": "Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mother of Nero and sister of Caligula married Claudius in 49 AD as a power play; she very probably poisoned Claudius four years later to ensure Nero would become emperor.",
        "answer": "Agrippina the Younger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Moses Beachy was a founding bishop of a group of these people, whose Buchanan subgroup is based in Iowa. The case Wisconsin v. Yoder ruled that these people were not required to be educated past eighth grade. These people generally reject hochmut, or pride, instead calling for Gelassenheit, or calmness. Lancaster, Pennsylvania is home to a community of, for ten points, what religious group with Anabaptist origins that split with the Mennonites in the 19th century and declines to adopt many modern technologies?",
        "answer": "Amish people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Some Amish communities permit this adolescent rite of passage in which teenagers may “run around” in the non-Amish world before being baptized as an adult member of the church.",
        "answer": "Rumspringa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was declared to be the rightful king in a letter sent to Pope John XXII, the Declaration of Arbroath. This man refused to rule jointly with John Comyn and instead killed Comyn in a church. This ruler agreed to the 1326 Treaty of Corbeil with France to renew the Auld Alliance. This man became Guardian after Edward I won a July 1298 battle against William Wallace, forcing Wallace to resign. Edward lost the 1314 Battle of Bannockburn to, for ten points, what Scottish king?",
        "answer": "Robert the Bruce or Robert I of Scotland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "William Wallace lost this 1298 battle to Edward I, after which he gave the Guardianship of Scotland to Robert the Bruce.",
        "answer": "Battle of Falkirk"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FDR’s Cabinet",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position briefly held by Nuremberg Trial prosecutor Robert Jackson, the head of the Justice Department.",
          "answer": "Attorney General"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position created in 1947 and first held by James Forrestal, who had been FDR’s Secretary of the Navy.",
          "answer": "Secretary of Defense"
        },
        {
          "question": "First woman to serve in the Cabinet; she served for FDR’s entire administration.",
          "answer": "Frances Perkins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position held by that woman.",
          "answer": "Secretary of Labor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agriculture and Commerce Secretary who also served as VP for FDR’s third term.",
          "answer": "Henry Agard Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State who won a Nobel Peace Prize in 1945.",
          "answer": "Cordell Hull"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-namesake of a university in Daytona Beach who coined the term “Black Cabinet” for FDR’s African-American advisers.",
          "answer": "Mary McLeod Bethune"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treasury Secretary and New Deal architect who proposed demilitarizing Nazi Germany.",
          "answer": "Henry Morgenthau, Jr."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Fascist Italy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city that was the target of a fascist march.",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fascist leader of Italy during World War II, called “Il Duce” [eel doo-chay].",
          "answer": "Benito Mussolini"
        },
        {
          "question": "Volunteer militia, named for the color of their uniform, that supported that leader.",
          "answer": [
            "Blackshirts",
            "Milizia Volontaria per la Sicurezza Nazionale",
            "MVSN",
            "Voluntary Militia for National Security",
            "Camicie Nere",
            "Camicia Nera",
            "squadristi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Expansionist goal promoted by Italy’s Spazio vitale [spatz-ee-oh vee-TAL-ay] and Nazi Germany’s Lebensraum [lay-bens-raum].",
          "answer": "living space"
        },
        {
          "question": "1939 alliance between Italy and Germany negotiated by Galeazzo Ciano.",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "stahlpakt",
            "Patto d’Acciaio"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1929 treaty that settled the Roman Question.",
          "answer": [
            "Lateran Treaty",
            "Patti Lateranensi",
            "Pacta Lateranensia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German puppet state that controlled the Northern half of Italy, established after an Allied invasion.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Salo",
            "Italian Social Republic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Father” of Italian fascism who ghostwrote a portion of The Doctrine of Fascism for an Italian Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "Giovanni Gentile"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assassinations",
      "prompt": "Name the assassinations...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Target of Operation Neptune Spear and leader of al-Qaeda.",
          "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caribbean leader who the CIA supposedly failed to kill in 638 different ways, including exploding cigars.",
          "answer": "Fidel Castro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of ISIS until his 2019 death by suicide during the Barisha raid.",
          "answer": "Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the Quds Force who was assassinated at Baghdad Airport in January 2020.",
          "answer": "Qasem Soleimani"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of South Vietnam who was killed in a 1963 CIA-backed coup.",
          "answer": "Ngo Dinh Diem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Target of Operation Vengeance, a Japanese admiral whose plane was shot down in 1943.",
          "answer": "Isoroku Yamomoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caribbean leader known as “el Jefe” [el HAY-fay] who was ambushed by his own military in 1961.",
          "answer": "Rafael Trujillo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Member of al-Qaeda who became the first US citizen targeted by a drone strike without due process in 2011.",
          "answer": "Anwar Nasser al-Awlaki"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This project’s employees included Lilli Hornig, who was initially given typist orientation instructions. Maria Goeppert Mayer won a Nobel Prize for her work done with this project. Leona Libby, a grad student at the University of Chicago, helped construct an experiment at (20 pts)",
        "Stagg Field for this project. Lise Meitner refused to work on this project, the subject of a 2014 book by Denise Kiernan about women brought to (10 pts)",
        "Oak Ridge, Tennessee. Chien-Shiung Wu provided troubleshooting advice to Enrico Fermi about neutron poisoning for, for ten points, what military research project, the subject of Kiernan’s The Girls of Atomic City, that produced the first atomic bombs?"
      ],
      "answer": "Manhattan Project"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man spent his final years as an ambassador to Britain, where he proposed a partition of Belgium at the London Conference. Earlier, this man concluded the Treaties of Luneville and Amiens to end the War of the (20 pts)",
        "Second Coalition. This man had diplomats Lucien Hauteval, Pierre Bellamy, and Jean Conrad Hottinguer informally (10 pts)",
        "demand bribes from an American delegation before they would be allowed to speak with him. The XYZ Affair involved, for ten points, what foreign minister who represented France at the Congress of Vienna?"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand-P´erigord"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man offered to duel Henry Clay after Clay struck him with a cane in retaliation for siphoning votes in the Election of 1840. Though this man suffered serious wounds at the Battle of Lundy’s Lane, he recovered and led U.S. Marines in storming (20 pts)",
        "Chapultepec castle in the Mexican-American War. This man’s most famous scheme called for the (10 pts)",
        "blockade of Southern ports after the outbreak of the Civil War. For ten points, name this general known as “Old Fuss and Feathers” who proposed the Anaconda Plan."
      ],
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, Gui Bonsiepe designed an operations room in accordance with Gestalt psychology. Stafford Beer and Fernando Flores helped implement a cybernetics program in this country. The state development company CORFO operated in this country, where Project (20 pts)",
        "Cybersyn was implemented. In 1970, Army commander Ren´e Schneider was fatally shot in a failed kidnapping supported by the CIA; three years later, an (10 pts)",
        "AK-47 given by Fidel Castro was used in the suicide of this country’s president. For ten points, name this country where Salvador Allende was overthrown in a coup led by Augusto Pinochet."
      ],
      "answer": "Chile"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Lincoln Steffens called Doc Ames the “shame of” this city, where mobster Kid Cann may have killed journalist Walter William Liggett. The American Indian Movement, or AIM, was founded in this city, where the Wounded Knee federal trial was held. Cadwallader Washburn and Charles (20 pts)",
        "Pillsbury owned competing flour mills that were powered by this city’s Saint Anthony Falls. In 2007, a bridge carrying I-35 across the (10 pts)",
        "Mississippi River collapsed in, for ten points, what member of the Twin Cities that is west of the capital, Saint Paul?"
      ],
      "answer": "Minneapolis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A book repudiating this man’s most famous achievement is marred by errors, including a claim that Giovanni de Marignolli was mentioned by name in a period document. This man’s embellishments include a story in which he taught the art of building mangonels to the (20 pts)",
        "Mongols. Fra Mauro’s world map depicting Asia may have been influenced by a map this man had. This man apparently failed to tell (10 pts)",
        "Rustichello da Pisa about chopsticks or a Great Wall in his stories of meeting Kublai Khan. For ten points, name this Venetian who traveled to China in the 13th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Marco Polo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s most famous work contains a seven-year hole later filled by the Hellenica. This man’s military experience in Corcyra led him to conclude that “war is a violent teacher.” The argument “the strong do what they can and the weak (20 pts)",
        "suffer what they must” is posed to the diplomats of Melos in a work by this man, who recorded a speech that ends “So died these men as becomes (10 pts)",
        "Athenians.” The funeral oration of Pericles is related by, for ten points, what author’s History of the Peloponnesian War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Thucydides"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Supporters of one candidate in this election year cut their hair and shaved their beards in an effort to “get clean for Gene” McCarthy, whose 42 percent in the New Hampshire primary caused the (20 pts)",
        "incumbent president to drop out. Abe Ribicoff spoke out against the “Gestapo tactics” used against protesters at this year’s (10 pts)",
        "DemocraticNationalConvention. Hubert Humphrey gained the Democratic nomination after the assassination of Robert Kennedy in, for ten points, what year in which Lyndon Johnson did not run for re-election and Richard Nixon was elected president?"
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1968"
    }
  ]
}